Turn your face to the Sun, child.
HELIS: My entire life I've always known one thing with prophetic certainty.
HELIS: That I was destined for glory as a great champion of the Sun.
HELIS: Even when Jiran was murdered, even when Meridian fell, I never doubted my destiny.
HELIS: Until you came along.
HELIS: When I heard that you had survived a doubt took root in my mind.
HELIS: As sure as the sun rises and falls each day, those I am bade to kill die.
HELIS: And yet I failed. How? Why?
HELIS: With each dig site you attacked, each loyal soldier you killed,
this pestering doubt grew.
It grew when High Priest Bahavas went missing.
And when the true Sun-King Itamen snatched away.
It not only grew but multiplied.
I kept thinking of the moment my knife pierced your throat.
One twist, a simple tug of the blade, and you would have bled out.
In slaughter I am a practised hand, so why hesitate?
Why fail my destined purpose?
See that scar on your cheek?
You didn't get to finish.
Yes, I remember.
He fought well for a savage.
His name was Rost and he was a better man than you could ever hope to be!
The better man is the one who doesn't end up with his guts steaming on the ground.
No, it wasn't him.
I could have finished you before he attacked, but I didn't.
I guess even a monster like you can have a glimmer of conscience.
"Turn your face to the sun, child."
Dressing up murder as religious sacrifice so you could feel better about it?
No, I never doubted the righteousness of killing you.
And yet, your words touch close to the truth.
In my heart, I deemed the order to kill you unworthy of me.
You were just a savage girl; so I thought at the time.
Even still, I aimed to kill you and yet did not.
This failing troubled my thoughts, haunted every step.
It was only when I captured you, down in that place, that I finally glimpsed the Sun's design etched at length across the course of events.
You were meant to survive that day on the mountain.
Meant to interfere at dig sites and kill my men.
Meant to eliminate High Priest Bahavas.
Meant to snatch Itamen away.
Conversely, I was meant to capture you.
Here.
So that you might die as a sacrificial offering to the Sun.
Everything as it was meant to be, predestined and preordained.
Spare me the religious justifications.
You can dress up your cruelty in holy clothes and words if you want.
But under it all, you're just a murderer.
An odd slight coming from you.
You've become quite a murderer yourself, child.
A killer of killers, not a murderer.
But I wouldn't expect you to know the difference.
All this talk of destiny and fate, I'm sure Hades speaks the same language, doesn't he?
You're being played for a fool.
It'd be laughable if there weren't so much killing involved.
Hades is an ancient machine, not the Buried Shadow of Carja myth.
It doesn't care about Meridian.
It wants to kill everything and everyone.
And you are its dutiful slave.
I serve not the Buried Shadow, but the Sun in shadow.
All halves of nature joined to one cause, shadow to sun, dark to light.
Do you really not hear how ridiculous that sounds?
You've gone from serving an insane homicidal Sun-King to an insane homicidal machine.
You're moving down in the world, not up.
I'll remember those words as I watch your corpse burn.
Whatever's left of it.
If you're gonna go on babbling like this all night, could you just kill me now?
Oh, no, we're in no hurry you and I, not now.
Maybe some physical torture to distract me from your voice?
You fail to grasp the point.
As surely as you've been conquered, so has all doubt.
And with certainty of belief comes unstoppable force.
Then open this cage and put your faith to the test.
See if things work out like you expect.
The circle has closed.
Every element is in its proper place, exactly where it belongs.
The errant beast, now caged, will serve her true purpose.
A sacrificial animal.
Oh, speaking of sacrifice, I forgot to tell you.
After you crashed the Eclipse network, I sent messengers into the east.
To rally the forces there and mount an invasion of the "sacred land".
I ordered every Nora killed.
I was hoping to catch you there, but, alas, it all seems to have been unnecessary.
Why butcher dozens of innocents for no gain? It's a waste of effort.
You're right. I won't even be there to enjoy it.
The Nora cast me out at birth.
You're not hurting me if you hurt them.
Really? Then it makes no difference one way or another.
You're an idiot. A dangerous idiot, but an idiot.
I couldn't recall the order even if I wished to.
Thanks to your destruction of the network, communication over distances is impossible.
You not only doomed yourself but an entire tribe.
Do we not see the scorching judgement of the Sun in these events?
Your Focus. Such a powerful device, isn't it?
And yet so fragile.
Aah, so you see, this time I did not hesitate.
The knife has already been twisted.
[crowd chanting and cheering]
HELIS: Carja faithful, rejoice!
Our years and shadow are over!
A new dawn trembles on the horizon!
A new day soon to break!
And when it does the false Sun-King will be dead, and Holy Meridian ours once more!
HELIS: In this I have become an instrument of prophecy.
All halves of nature joined to one cause, shadow to sun, light to dark, night to day.
Behold!
Hold your seats!
Can you not see the proof of the Sun's blessing before your eyes?
HELIS: How else could shadows such as these prowl in broad light of day?
HELIS: Were they not approved by the Sun and joined to our cause?
HELIS: Many years ago to consecrate this great ring the Radiant Jiran
ordered many faithless crushed beneath the hooves of a Behemoth.
HELIS: Mighty is the Behemoth in the eye of the Sun.
HELIS: But it is mightier still infused with the power of shadow.
HELIS: Let this one who schemed and slivered be the first to die!
Let her be the first of thousands!
I'll never beat that thing without weapons.
Gotta get out of the way.
All my weapons are up on the platform, and there's no way out of this ring.
One more pillar and that platform will come down, and my weapons with it!
That did it!
Hey! Guess who got her weapons back!
Now you're just a big, dumb target.
Come and get it!
Silence!
Shadows, kill her!
KILL HER!
Why leave it to them? Come get me yourself!
Sylens?
TRAITOR!
So you're here. Really here.
You risked your life.
Of course I did.
How did you track my location when I wasn't wearing a Focus?
Really, Aloy, it doesn't take a genius to surmise that Helis would throw you into the Sun-Ring at high noon.
Helis recognised you back in the Sun-Ring.
You told me that you assisted the Eclipse.
Not that you knew the man who killed my…
Who almost killed me.
So now you know.
The man is a serious threat, so let's do all we can to make sure that he and Hades don't succeed.
Right.
I wore out two Striders getting here in time, but I did.
Since when can you override machines?
Ever since you discovered the technique.
I had to destroy a Corruptor to obtain the necessary parts, of course.
But your example showed me how to do that as well.
Yet another benefit of monitoring your activities through your Focus.
Truth be told, the underlying logic of the technique isn't so different from rites
practices by Banuk Shamans.
Though, of course, far more advanced.
Great. You're welcome, I guess.
If you'd been killed, the Nora's sacred mountain would never have given up its secrets.
Too bad you wasted your time then.
Helis destroyed my Focus and the Alpha Registry with it.
Not at all.
The whole time I've been monitoring your Focus, I've duplicated every data file you've scanned.
Installing that data to a new Focus was trivially easy.
"Happy birthday, Isaac. Daddy sure does love his little big man."
You're really good at making it impossible to like you, Sylens.
But I guess I need this.
It's time to see where you were born.
Maybe you'll even learn why.
Yeah, "meet the machine that birthed me into this world."
Isn't that how you put it?
When you were recovering The Alpha Registry down in the Zero Dawn bunker I was needlessly cruel.
For your sake, I hope there is someone waiting there for you inside the mountain.
Not a what, but a who.
Helis ordered an Eclipse detachment to attack the Nora's Sacred Land.
The tribe's already weak, they won't stand a chance. You should come with me.
Oh, absolutely not. I have preparations to make elsewhere.
What kind of… hmph, why do I bother asking?
You're not gonna tell me.
When the time is right I'll be in touch.
I'll contact you later.
In the meantime, should you need to return to Shadow Carja territory I brought armour to conceal your identity.
You think of everything, don't you?
One of us has to.
Now be on your way.
Yah!
0:21.33.000,0:21.37.000
Another day, what will this one hold?
They're scanning for me.
Well, I guess I can't blame you for that.
Let's see you catch us!
Always watching.
That smell, trees on fire.
The Embrace!
The Watchtower's burning, but the sentinels had time to warn the tribe.
Seeker, you've returned.
Where is everyone?
They fell back, took shelter inside the Sacred Mountain.
But the faithless and their demons pursued.
Can I help you?
Please leave me, help others.
I am beyond your help.
Go! I will beg the goddess to guide you, Seeker.
[flashback]
MAREA: Trying to live up to the glory of the Nora hasn't killed me yet.
MAREA: But if it has to, I'm willing.
Marea. She wasn't one to give up ground.
Well she didn't sell her life cheaply.
In the end I guess that's all any of us can hope for.
Let's get on with it!
It'd be fascinating, if they weren't looking for me.
The Nora made a stand here.
Anything to protect the Embrace.
But the gates couldn't hold.
This is Hades' future, metal and ash.
The Embrace, it's devastated!
For years, this … this was my entire world.
It can be destroyed in hours?
No birdsong. I've never heard the Embrace so quiet, so dead.
Got their attention!
ECLIPSE: Who's firing at me?
ECLIPSE: Huh?
ECLIPSE: I can hear you, I think—
You can see them, they can't see you.
ECLIPSE: She's coming for us!
That's right, no-one here.
Another battle, another defeat.
The Eclipse smashed through.
ECLIPSE: Got eyes—
ECLIPSE: Here!
Haven't you got anything better to do?
ECLIPSE: You cannot escape!
ECLIPSE: Eh?
ECLIPSE: The Sun can't save you now!
More Eclipse.
It's a Corrupted Thunderjaw, alright.
The survivors must be holed up in the mountain.
If the tunnel collapses, they'll be buried.
And I'll never reach the hatch.
ECLIPSE: That's right. Bring down the mountain!